A Guide to the Papers of the Noland Family, 1774 [1813-1899] 1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Noland Family 1774 [1813-1899] 1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6463, -a, -c, -d
This collection consists of ca. 4,000 items (8 Hollinger boxes, 3.4 cubic feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Noland papers were given to the Library on several occasions. Accession 6463, 6463-c, and 6463-d were a gift of Mrs. William C. Noland of Richmond, Virginia on November 25, 1960, May 14, and August 26, 1980. Accession 6463-a was a gift of Nelson B. Noland of Birmingham, Michigan on May 18, 1962.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of ca. 4,000 items (8 Hollinger boxes, 3.4 cubic feet), 1774 [1813-1899] 1947, chiefly the papers of the Noland family of Airwell, Hanover County, Virginia, particularly Callender St. George Noland [1816- ], his parents William Noland [1775?- ], Catherine (Callender) Noland [1775?-1849], his wife Mary Edmonia (Berkeley) Noland, and their children Nelson B. Noland [1846-1913], Francis Noland [d. 1898], William Churchill Noland, and Margaret B. Noland, and also of the Rev. John Cooke, guardian of Mary E. B. Noland.
The bulk of the collection consists of the correspondence of the family members with friends, acquaintances, and Naval officials. A few originate in other states and countries particularly Madagascar, Mexico, Brazil, Germany, and Peru. Also in the collection are Cooke's guardianship accounts for Mary Berkeley, some letters from him, and two diaries, 1831 and 1854.
Callendar St. George Noland's papers cover his career in the U. S. Navy including an Everglades expedition in 1841 and charges brought against him for flogging two Marine privates, 1842, his life at Airwell and his Civil War service in the artillery at Fort Powhatan and later in the Confederate Naval Department.
The letters of Nelson B. Noland describe life at the Virginia Military Institute during the Civil War including preparations for the battle of New Market, his work on the Peruvian Hydrographic Commission of the Amazon, 1872-1874, and his later efforts to receive payment, his work for the Boston Silver Company, Sts. John Summit County, Colorado and life as a mining engineer in Kokomo, Colorado. Letters of Francis Noland describe teaching at Strawberry Plains, Isle of Wight County, Virginia, Gainesville, Alabama, frontier life in Commanche, Texas, and Kokomo, Colorado, where he worked for the Summit County Times and the Denver and Rio Grande Railroad. His letters also describe Indian troubles, claim jumping, a murder and a lynching, and life in Norfolk, Virginia where he worked for the Norfolk Virginian, Norfolk Landmark, and Portsmouth Times before becoming chief of ordnance for the U. S. Navy in 1886. His letters from Norfolk describe local personalities, polities, foreign vessels in port including Russian and British warships, the 1885 bank failure, and his naval duties. Several of his articles and essays are included. William Churchill Noland's letters describe life as a student at Episcopal High, Fairfax County, Virginia, as an architectural student with the firm of Theophilus Chandler, Philadelphia, and as an employee of Edward H. Kendall, New York; drawings and a commonplace book are included. Also in the correspondence are routine naval business letters from George Bancroft, George Campbell Read, James Cochran Dobbin, John Young Mason, Abel P. Upshur, and Levi Woodbury. Other correspondents include Thomas Nelson Page, who offers advice on a Civil War story in 1896, VMI superintendent, Francis Henney Smith, Richmond business man Lewis D. Aylett, Frank Noland's potential business partner Philip Pendleton Cooke, Colorado engineer, George T. McDonald, Amazon expedition president John Randolph Tucker and members F. C. Galt and James H. Rocelle, Boston businessman J. F. Spofford, Virginia Land Company vice-president A. J. Milliken, and Richmond Petersburg Railway Road Company superintendent E. T. D. Myers.
There are also various Berkeley family papers which consist primarily of financial and legal papers and some correspondence. Accounts of Nelson Berkeley and Lewis Berkeley for estate settlements of Thomas N. Berkeley and Carter B. Berkeley and the guardianship of Elizabeth Edmonia Churchill Berkeley, 1817-1835, are present. Related items include slave lists and accounts from Airwell and Dewberry, Hanover County, including a sermon, and a slave insurance policy.
Other items in the collection consist of school essays and exams, diaries, a carpenter's and [builder's?] time and memoranda books, photographs, architectural drawings, Confederate tax records and souvenirs, including reunion ribbons and a piece of a flag from General "Stonewall" Jackson's grave.
Arrangement
The papers of the two families in the collection have been interfiled and arranged chronologically. Correspondence is filed first followed by Financial and Legal Papers, Sermons, Essays and Articles, Miscellaneous Papers, Printed Materials, Photographs, Drawings and Sketches, Bound Volumes, and Oversize. Papers regarding the guardianship account of Mary Edomnia Berkeley were arranged chronologically within a single folder and filed within the financial and legal papers. Loose items from the bound volumes are in inserts which were numbered according to the volumes from which they were removed.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1823-1872, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1873-1880 Jul, 6 folders (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1880 Aug-1883 May, 7 folders (Box 3)
- 1883 Jun-1885 May (Box 4)
- Correspondence 1885 Jun-1899, n.d., 8 folders (Box 5)
- Correspondence n.d., 3 folders (Box 6)
- Financial and Legal Papers re Guardianship Account of Mary Edmonia Berkeley 1828-1840 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous Papers and Memorabilia 1827-1947, n.d. (Box 7)
- School Papers 1840-1881, n.d., 2 folders (Box 7)
- Sermons, Essays, and Articles 1813-1891, n.d. (Box 7)
- Printed Material 1774, 1814-1896 (Box 7)
- Newspaper Clippings 1868-1898, n.d. (Box 7)
- Photographs, Drawings and Sketches 1836, 1883, 1891, n.d. (Box 7)
- Diaries 1824 & 1825 (Box 8)
- Diaries of Rev. [John Cooke?] 1831 & 1839 (Box 8)
- Policy, Franklin Fire Insurance Company of Philadelphia, issued to St. George Noland 1848 (Box 8)
- Pencil drawing with printed legend, The Modern "Crusoe" n.d. (Box 8)
- Pencil drawing, Cottage by ruined tower n.d. (Box 8)
- Ledger of [Callender St. George?], later used as a sketchbook by William Noland 1850-1852 (Box 8)
- Account Book of Callender St. George Noland 1853 (Box 8)
- Diary of [Mrs. John Cooke?] 1854 (Box 8)
- Builder's Pay Roll and Memoranda Book 1885 (Box 8)
- Memoranda Book of N. H. Noland from Offley Mill, Hanover County, Virginia 1886 (Box 8)
- Carpenter's Time and Pay Book of Edgewood 1886-1887 (Box 8)
- Commonplace Book of William C. Noland ca. 1880-1890 (Box 8)
- Diary of [?] 1899 (Box 8)
- Diary of [?] ca. 1900 (Box 8)
- Papers pulled from various volumes 1875-1886, n.d. (Box 8)